A Guide to the Waterford Town Council Minute Book, 1891-1911
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Waterford Town Council Minute Book 1891-1911
Thomas Balch Library
OMB 014, AV 005
This collection consists of a digital and a paper copy of one volume of minutes and accounts relating to the administrative functions of the incorporated town board of Waterford, VA, 1891-1911. Topics discussed in the minutes include the appointment and election of town officials and judges, town boundaries, street maintenance, and the collections of taxes. Town accounts are entered at the end of the volume.
Loudoun County Attorney's Office, Leesburg, VA.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Loudoun County Attorney's Office, Leesburg, VA.
Alternative Form Available
Electronic media
Historical Information
Amos Janney (1700-1746) founded Waterford in 1733 after accepting a large parcel of land in exchange for surveying services to Thomas, 6th Lord Fairfax (1693-1791). He added several thousand acres to his original parcel and established a mill, thus giving the area its original name, Janney's Mill. Janney was a member of the Society of Friends and came to the area from Bucks County, Pennsylvania. Many other Quakers from Bucks County and the surrounding areas followed him to Virginia, and Janney's Mill quickly became a commercial center. The village officially became known as Waterford in the 1780s and was incorporated by the Virginia General Assembly in 1836. Prior to the Civil War, Waterford was Loudoun County's second largest town after Leesburg.
Waterford's growth stagnated in the mid-19th century, and the Civil War took a heavy toll on the town. Initially Waterford occupied a prime location for trade with easy access to Leesburg and ferry points across the Potomac River. In the 1830s, a railroad to Point of Rocks, Maryland opened north of Waterford and Snickersville Turnpike opened south of the village. Waterford, thus bypassed, was no longer a center for trade. In the years leading up to the Civil War, disheartened by Virginia's reluctance to abandon slavery, Quakers began leaving Waterford and migrating to Ohio. Because the Quakers of Waterford were abolitionists and pacifists the village was harassed by Confederate forces. Many fled north and the population of Waterford dwindled further.
The town unincorporated in 1936. Today the village is largely residential. The Waterford Historic District was listed as a Virginia Historic Landmark in 1969.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of a digital and a paper copy of one volume of minutes and accounts relating to the administrative functions of the incorporated town board of Waterford, VA, 1891-1911. Topics discussed in the minutes include the appointment and election of town officials and judges, town boundaries, street maintenance, and the collections of taxes. Town accounts are entered at the end of the volume.
The original minute book was included in a court record in the files of the Loudoun County Attorney. The court record was transferred to the Library of Virginia (LVA) in accordance with Records Retention and Disposition Schedules for state and local public records. LVA then microfilmed and scanned the minute book and placed the original in its collections.
Arrangement
Folder
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
History of Waterford, Virginia: A National Historic Landmark. www.waterfordhistory.org (accessed 29 May 2012).
Janney, Werner and Asa Moore. Ye Meetg Hous Smal: A Short Account of Friends in Loudoun County, Virginia 1732-1980. Lincoln, VA: by the authors, 1980.
Waterford Foundation. Walk With Us Through Waterford, Virginia: A National Historic Landmark District. Waterford, VA: Waterford Foundation, 2005.
Location of Originals
Library of Virginia
Technical Requirements
Electronic Media
Related Material
Map of Waterford, 1875, Map Collection, Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Separated Material
None
Contents List
- (OMB 014)
  - Title pages from microfilm and digital versions
  - Loose pages found throughout minute book
  - Cover-page 19, 1 Jul 1891-21 Jun 1893
  - pages 20-41, 20 Jun 1893-5 Jun 1896
  - pages 42-64, 30 Jun 1896-30 Jun 1898
  - pages 65-87, 3 Jul 1898-7 May 1900
  - pages 88-110, 4 Jun 1900-2 Dec 1901
  - pages 111-113, 13 Jan 1901-22 Dec 1903
  - pages 134-159, 2 Feb 1904-14 Dec 1905
  - pages 160-186, 2 Jan 1906-2 Jun 1907
  - pages 187-226, 31 Aug 1907-2 Sep 1909
  - pages 229-back cover (accounts), 1891-1911
- (AV 005)
  - 2 CDs containing digital images of minute book